A true story of innocence lost and courage found.
Born on the Fourth of July is a drama, war film directed by Oliver Stone.
Paralyzed in the Vietnam war, Ron Kovic becomes an anti-war and pro-human rights
political activist after feeling betrayed by the country he fought for.
Ron Kovic, played by Tom Cruise.
Mr. Kovic, played by Raymond J. Barry.
Mrs. Kovic, played by Caroline Kava.
Donna, played by Kyra Sedgwick.
Charlie, played by Willem Dafoe.
Steve Boyer, played by Jerry Levine.
Born on the Fourth of July is a 1989 American biographical anti-war drama
film that is based on the 1976 autobiography of Ron Kovic.
Directed by Oliver Stone, and written by Stone and Kovic, it
stars Tom Cruise, Kyra Sedgwick, Raymond J.
Barry, Jerry Levine, Frank Whaley, and Willem Dafoe.
The film depicts the life of Kovic (Cruise) over a 20-year period, detailing his childhood, his military
service and paralysis during the Vietnam War, and his transition to anti-war activism.
It is the second installment in Stone's trilogy of films about the Vietnam War,
following Platoon (1986) and preceding Heaven & Earth (1993).
Producer Martin Bregman acquired the film rights to the book in 1976 and hired Stone, also a Vietnam
veteran, to co-write the screenplay with Kovic, who would be played by Al Pacino.
When Stone optioned the book in 1978, the film adaptation became mired in development hell after
Pacino and Bregman left, which resulted in him and Kovic putting the film on hold.
After the success of Platoon, the project was revived at
Universal Pictures, with Stone attached to direct.
Shot on locations in the Philippines, Texas and Inglewood, California, principal
photography took place from October to December 1988, lasting 65 days of filming.
The film went over its initial $14 million production budget and
ended up costing $17.8 million after reshoots.
Upon release, Born on the Fourth of July was praised by critics for
its story, Cruise's performance and Stone's direction.
The film was successful at the box office as it grossed over $162 million
worldwide, becoming the tenth highest-grossing film of 1989.
At the 62nd Academy Awards, it received eight nominations, including Best Picture and Best Actor for Cruise, his first
nomination, and the film won for Best Director, Stone's second in that category, and Best Film Editing.
The film also won four Golden Globe Awards for Best Motion Picture – Drama, Best
Actor – Motion Picture Drama, Best Director and Best Screenplay.
The film explores themes of vietnam war, vietnam veteran,
post-traumatic stress disorder (ptsd), 1970s, wheelchair.
The tone is emotional.